I think we need to reconsider what alive
and not alive actually means because the
line is getting very blurry. Recently,
we've discovered that you can revive a
brain after expiration. In fact, you can
keep it alive for a few days, but it's
not really conscious, right? I mean, it
doesn't have the brain function that we
associate with a conscious patient. But,
perhaps we are not more than the sum of
our parts because recent research has
found that pieces of your brain, slices
of your brain can continue to remain
active after you are no longer here. In
fact, not only can they be active, but
they can learn to control a robot hand
and play the piano. I mean, researchers
have also been able to take cells from
frogs from frogs that are you know, no
longer here and turn them into biobots
or xenobots. Yes, they can be mobile,
they can eat, and they can even
reproduce, but are they robots or are
they an animal? I really don't have the
answers to that.
Now, when it comes to the consciousness
question, I would say that it's unlikely
that the brain slices are having any
kind of an experience like you or I are
having, although I can't be sure because
we can't really be sure about anything.
Somebody did point out that there was a
man in France that was operating with
just 90% of his brain, and he didn't
even know that this was the case till
much later into his 40s. In fact, he had
a normal IQ and just had some issues
with movement.
This is of course a rather extreme
example, and there's no reason to think
that things like lab-grown brains or
brain slices have any form of
consciousness. It's just that we don't
understand it very well. I actually get
a little bit upset when people say
something like brain organoids or even
AI could never be conscious because they
just can't, they're not that sort of
thing. I don't think it's reasonable
because we don't really know what
consciousness is, nor sentience, nor do
we have any way to measure it. The more
I learn about consciousness and
intelligence, the more I'm starting to
think that the concept is a
philosophical question and not a
scientific one.
As much as I like to make fun of
philosophy, I'm just not a huge fan. I
do think that it has some value, and
this is the time for it to shine. How
can we know if something is conscious,
be it an AI or a lab-grown brain or a
piece of brain that has been excised
from someone who is no longer alive and
is now operating a robot?
Servitors, we may be on the path to
servitors. I mean, I'm not totally mad
about it. It is fascinating.
On the other side of that equation, some
people are trying to reach immortality
with digital twins. Chatbots are trying
to create an AI with all of the stuff
that they might know. You might even be
able to record brain activity and create
a spiking neural network, though an AI
that's based on spiking patterns in the
brain, and turn that into a twin. But,
is it really you? I would say not.
I'm not even saying that it could never
be conscious because I don't know that.
I don't know what kind of technological
advancements we'll have, and I'm really
not sure the distinction matters, but I
just I don't think that it constitutes
you.
Unfortunately, we may have to answer
some questions in the near future, like
what rights that a chatbot might have.
I'm also reasonably concerned with the
misbehavior we see in AI, including
self-defense-like behaviors, that
somebody is going to have a companion
bot, and that companion bot is going to
try to protect itself. Mark my words, it
will happen. I'll probably be the person
who tells you about it.
The point is that brand new research on
what a brain can learn or do after
expiration or even what cells can learn
and do has been totally turned on its
head. I mean, we've only been able to
clone for so long. I think we're going
to have to reapproach what alive and not
alive really means, and it's certainly
going to be interesting.
I hope you've enjoyed this. I will keep
you up to date. In fact, you have no
choice. Look for more.
>> Are you carrying on with the
tiny prokaryotes here?